You can I think they're ready to go on the sessionthank you for joining us so,
today we're going to talk about that well the topic is tried-and-true practices
for transforming sharepoint solutions that...ready solutions and this is something
that we've been actually working within the microsoft for quite a long-time with many of the customers as well so
...helping...about while quite a few of our fisheries histogram
...customers to transform their customizations from the fortunes
...solutions and...solutions...solutions and my name is special
you want I'm senior program manager in office traces the five engineering and,
I'm also to technical late or the coordination...for the patterns and practices guidance for fisheries
...and I'm steve walker I'm also senior program manager I'm on the
...sixty-five extensibility team previously I was on the same team is...we still
work very closely together patterns and practices...came out of like
...said working with a lot of our customers who were trying to move away
from their traditional development practices so everything that you'll see here today or things that we've actually
done real customers you can also get all this code and much more yourself
and very easy way to download consumes...show you a lot of that as we as we move
forward good before we actually star test out of curiosity how many of you are actually sharepoint
developers on just looking...of...room we were kind of
expecting dancer to be honest because they're quite a high computation at the same time on the time
...and how many of you are actually shipment implementing sharepoint apps?
So, that's half of sauced more than a half which means that half of the
...doing fortunes code which is absolutely fully...of
...so no down and but with gradually of thinking true how do we make the
translation that a new way of implementing does customizations and this is what this session is all
abound and we will have...discussion kind of a high-level
...even a business or process level discussion about want us
to transformation actually means so one of what is the learning's what we've been doing with the
customers during the past two years and how do we approach transformation
projects and we will be also revealing some of that stuff fun, for example,
releasing templates and process guidance and msdn pretty soon as I on this topic us well
...so definitely help on your...deals online the...transformation projects and with the
customers as well and we also want to make sure that we give you a learnings from the
real-life translations so essentially
...samples because we actually do this for living as a full-time
...job pretty much well you not that much anymore within a new role
...just waving your hands but ...all...getting and,
then what we wanted to do is that we...make kind of...
few typical sharepoint app model customizations transformations what does it mean and what's,
what's actually to advent the...of moving the cloud data...repeat some of the
...done previously,... tech at
...because you've probably seen some of...demos as well but...wanted to make slightly more
...scenarios...want to show really well how...how you can take advantage of the microsoft
usher at to really be the engine for your...five
and cloud based implementations if you're doing on prime ad their slightly different alternatives to
do similar staff but let's talk about those during demos as well and,
we definitely want to show you the rubric
...testify patterns and practices provisioning engine what's will help you
to create templates and template ing systems within the cloud...this really,
really new stuff what's not getting really,
really stable just this week...just this week actually the,...
the first introduction window went live during this way so we really want to show that
pointy practice for us now if you have any questions and hopefully get as excited
...we are on that engine which should help the failed on data...of the cloud?
Yeah, so, for those we haven't seen it, you know, we do have a fairly compelling developer vision it's
...just a little bit we still absolutely believe in what traditionally
folks would call office after sharepoint...which is really what's over on the
user's side of the equation so we call those contextual application so putting
application surfacing them where users are doing their work and, then that really where a lot of
our investments now are really on this data side so you'll hear us talking about three
sixty five api and you'll hear us talking about all of the great api endpoints that
we're doing a across not just sharepoint but also the rest of the workloads
so that's one thing I want you guys to walker to things there's two things I would walk out of this room today
when you think about this developer vision is one we still care about the your traditional scenario...going to
unlock new scenarios across the sweet so you're not just going to be a sharepoint developer you'll be able to develop
a gift exchange and other areas of...sixty-five so, you'll hear a lot of folks actually
we'll talk about that in a few minutes...saying why should I learn this thing when there's that new three
sixty five api thing those things will come together and they're going
to come together very soon so the investments that you're making today on either side of this
of investments that will payoff in the future of should you start to build standalone
...things that ager we do have an actually quite nice announcements at related on the
...as well on that one so one of the things
...wanted to do also within the session let's say we wanted to start with the common kind
...statements what the field this...to us all the times when one of make really share that you understand what
...talking when we moved adapt model what doesn't actually mean and what are the steps and also the
statements related on sharepoint asher server...as an example related on the full
...to related on up...so you will have quite a few slides
as an introduction topic which are having statements and then going to work venture to
get within the audience before we move into does demos on data topics and but,
we really want to make sure that you understand when I talk about the app model transformation it actually
means of rewrite it really means that you cannot actually...server-side code
and test magically...of with some magical tooling what's will suddenly come up
within app model implementation that's not reality because quite often we need to
think about completely alternative ways to light up the same functionality using the end
up model techniques and I would say when I was still in the field when I would engage
...these projects quite often I would go into a
customer we're not even transforming to a different model but you would step back and look at what they've built a new
would decide that maybe there's a better way to do this I used I used to use a story where I went
into a customer one-time and they were having some challenges with
their sharepoint implementation and I go in and I look...inventory of the customizations and
they had fifty-five master pages they had a hundred and eighty six page
layout or noam's ninety...page layouts and they had a hundred eighty six unique dot net web
parts they had written and you of course that sounds a little sketchy when you when...say that so,
we dove...we rolled up our sleeves and what we ended up with
was one master page about six page layouts and we replace ninety percent of those web
parts with a out-of-the-boxcontent query what parts so, you know,
this is an excellent opportunity
to look at what has been developed before and if there's a better way to do it?
And, that's really the...point to understand the functionality
and the business requirements they're not going to go away...what we need to do is think about ok is
the business requirements on there and we can absolutely have...and, we need to have the discussion with
the customer do we need to still actually have this capability what does it mean within the app model is
this birth of the investment quite often what...within the...that was one customer had one
hundred twenty double sp...says within the dedicated form
...actually eighty nine of them where waste ...trying to
win so we were able to concentrate on twenty-one or whatever we ended up being
...looking to the actual functionality which when it to transform so the functionality
...for comments is still there and, that's usually the case even in a farm solution implementation...
steaks the longest time the technical implantation when of think of it that's relatively simple in the
end but figuring out what the custom actually once not so...the difficult part
...fact that...deploying the must debates using a module element in
a feature framework or rb pushing that using see some add to the cloud
our on premises that's kind of a technical newman's internet-related
doesn't care and the customer typically doesn't care that's absolutely true and one of the
...which...common also kind of question what we common cats is that do we have any
excess thing tool...we can run true to magical
...solution...put magically come of the not model solution the reality is
that we don't and the transformation is such a unique thing...we need to look on the
function nowadays one by one we don't have a tool which will just metric come up with a
app model implementation we do have create tools however for the assessment boston so
we're able to understand what to customize actually having rightnow within the...but it's not about
the technology actually it's more about one that's the functionality enables from...perspective.
One of the things what we also want to make sure that is that the common question well-defined solutions
...in sharepoint server...will be absolutely...and say what we want
to do is continue if you haven't taken at...previous investments in
...solutions and you don't have an opportunity to transform that's absolutely fine
and it comes down and they will be supported and sharepoint server
...sixteen...investments are however done on that model
...even in on premises we really want people actually move
the daffodil gradually so that the implant once and it will work in on premises or in
cloud whenever the if the customize moving that...our running the staff and premises...I just
...by the saying here today we know that there's been a huge ecosystem and
...install base of sharepoint built up over the years I've made a
live-in for ten years out in
the field doing nothing but building on top of sharepoint so these things are going to just go
away tomorrow we know that we need to have a story that's going to a allow you to use the
...you made on prim but, what we're seeing more and more is the financial model of office
...sixty-five is so compelling things like terabytes of one drive storage that you're going to
start to see your customers or your customer that you are the company
you work out want to move that direction right and we're not saying you
need to throw out the baby with the bath water we want to make sure that you can continue to use what
you have today...extend that surface area into the cloud and rewrite
...things as they make sense that's the same approach we took within microsoft I actually
helped drive our initial implementation towards the cloud and, we ended up making a conscious
decision to leave behind a good number of our intranet properties
until such time as we could we could rewrite them just because nobody had budget for it
and it wasn't it wasn't time to do that so you'll hear a lot of things out in the
blogs clear that you sound very controversial read them with a grain of salt and
...if you action amiss and really get...so one of quite often when...do to...to the
cloud alway evaluate...the customers having that there's a lot of solutions which are
...end up being having...hyper deployment that some solutions which doesn't really make any
sense to make a significant investment to rewrite that does not model implementation we leave that
...premises but we'd take the maturity of the things...move them to the
cloud and that's where we need to have that discussion with
the business owners who actually know what where the solution is and what's the value of the solutions
...one of the common questions this is pretty...already should be and what we have a support...solutions and
...as defined never that's never going to...so,
this is a pretty clear and we will do all of our investments and sharepoint apple
...or well technically to sharepoint add-in science now
...changing the marketing term
at sharepoint app essentially sharepoint adding a starting from like today
...that's my and I'll start to see entirely new experiences that are built the only have
extensibility in this new model I can't call out any specifically right off the top of
my head but you'll start to see that moving forward where that's the preferred method that
we would like to see people utilize I mean there's benefit not just for us in our
cloud, you know, obviously we have a huge incentive to keep our service stable and you have a
financially backed sla for service like this allowing somebody else to inject code into
your worker process is a huge risk with your financially liable for so let's not even, you know,
take up a technical thing because I get that a lot hey you guys could do better, you know,
you guys could run this with my custom code you've done it for years
and your dedicated environment you're right it's expensive and it's really risky and it's not something
we're ever going to do and...sixty-five we've I don't know that we've come across
a scenario that's common that we haven't been able to do in the app model and turn, you know,
we'd love to hear it if you if you find those were listening we'll talk with the into the session about how you
can submitfeedback to us on things that you find challenging or that your...but
just know that this is not something that I don't care if everybody in the world said we want you to install
ws...and...sixty-five there's some real challenges to that both from a technical problem
space and the business side...and like I said we are highly committed on making sure that the if it's
...missing api...api some need to have...will actually make
it available unless it's a farm administrative operation
and thousands because we can actually expose those within...which is understandable
it's a journey and where on the...and we've been enabling lot-of new api within a...as well...
if you've been following up on what's actually happening and one of the things...also quite often here from the
customers is the following statement iso...the internet saying that...model
...not let's make sure we might be changing the terminology it's no
...sharepoint app model...to sharepoint adding but that doesn't mean that the technology
or the implementation or the investments what...done in a shipment that model would actually go away
...these loosely coupled interfaces and interacting with our products via these interfaces is the
model of the future we call that in general the app model you know,
the way I used to like to look at it and the way I've been explaining it recently is that
...on premised product like sharepoint that is that
extensible you can pretty much just change-up any piece of it that you want if you don't like what we're
doing there was great our in that we really were just...interface and you could change-up pieces
...the front-side in the back side you...a lot of control right and I did it visited it
you know, there was times I replaced eighty percent of the user controls and things that were in those
master pages just make exactly what we wanted now when you move the
cloud it's more of an abstract class you can't go switching out the pieces on the back...so you have
to think about these things a little differently how you're going to achieve the same and goals but,
this is really the model that...doubling down on and I think just to kind of reinforce
that if you want to click to the next slide this is out of our dog food environment
...pb environment but I really just wanted-to call-up and show you guys?
The...the teams...there where when you're building one of these apps you'll be able to
...with active directory so the existing
app model for sharepoint twenty thirteen is actually backed by as...access a...and,
then all of our new autry sixty-five api investments that you're hearing about...backed by abstracted directory and
technology called common consent that allows us to work across workloads so...was very much
of silo for sharepoint abstracted directory lets us kind of break out of the sharepoint
jailing go across these other workloads so do things like work with exchange do things like work with link
...even work with third parties through open id connect so,
these are the investments that we're making we're doing nothing but making the app model better and moving towards a
common out model from an author animosity perspectives so I think it
super important that you castaway the fear uncertainty and doubt when you see those types of
blog posts that try to state that we're moving in a different direction because we're just flat-out not
...is the direction we're going to the only...if you think about...technology perspective it's not just the
only way that we're going to be able to run a service that has the types of...we have
you that's the only way that we're going to get out to all these other endpoints right so we now have office on we now have
office on android devices and we want those types of experiences to be able light up
...those platforms so we need to do this in a very loosely couple cross platform way.
Good and that's the
...final statement not going to do more than all of this lines but seriously this system
...heading this is whether investments on done and whenever you have a chance
...stumble jump on that train and then gradually start moving on the same direction by the
product setting and that's why we have programs...faces divine developed
by than some practices which is helping the farm solution and the classic service signed
developers then translation...model...lighting up
on showing how-to-do-it typical customizations using the app model techniques the whole thinking of the of
gap was definitely the fact...developer you don't need to think about and,
cloud as an exception...premises and extraction we implement one piece of code
the and implantation...a coupled implementation and it works within the
...artworks within the on premises so it's a one implementation of the whole thing
and that's really the key and foundation of things more and more customers some moving that the
...so we really need to make sure that the staff what we
...it is capable up and running in on premises on a cloud of smoke pulling just like we you know,
we built this pattern so that we could upgrade our servers and services and
...sixty-five without you have to worry about your custom code
...to be touched that was incredibly huge amount of labor that we would go through for an upgrade cycle in
are dedicated environment as an example which is representative of
what everyone was pretty much doing I'm going to up install service pack one...sharepoint
...desi better go make sure all your stuff still works with service pack one
you go through that whole cycle so by moving to this loosely coupled
architecture your infrastructure guys get unlocked to be able to move a little faster and you get
...from having to do all of that maintenance work every time to see what we've changed with
the...api which before we got the
...demos and, start going to the code one of the things...we also want to...relay...
website make sure that you vassar developer understand the direction so,
you think about dot model and app and agnes and the sharepoint that
...we essentially can categorized sharepoint customization in tree different
models and exploding of...on but solution because that's kind of the bile simulate
...functionality what it is worth bringing up here so there are folks
and say well I've already invested heavily in sandbox solutions what am I going to do am I...have to rewrite all
that no we will be supporting that for the foreseeable future
and our cloud we will not be making investments there if you put twenty web
parts on a page to anybody here ever put twenty sandbox what parts of...page you guys are all smart, you know,
what's going to happen if you raise the bugged to
us and said that pages performing slow we're going to shake our heads and say yes,
it is...if you do that that's going to always be slow so there are some known limitations
sandbox solutions but don't think that we're just going to
...rug out from underneath you just yet but, I would if you're moving from full trust
code I would not I would not recommend that you look at moving to sandbox just because it
feels a little easier the investment that you're going to make is actually probably about the same as totally go
into the app model and you're going to be jump...one step ahead.
Which and, on the...so,...think about the let's say the tree ways of having chevron
customizations on the left side we have the classic while encodes classic apertures got solutions
...opponents...the only challenge...dot one is that it's not...office traces to five and never
will be because we can actually have photos code running and...information
on the right side we have to store apps and that's a typical way about how people visualize
the sharepoint and they think about us...which are in office store and you're able to download and down their
...apps and then they run javascript and that's not actually
...whole story we have the middle section as well which
is essentially client-side solutions remote provisioning staff what we actually
enabled within the science by running javascript, for example,
as an embedded javascript within the side itself it doesn't have to be
a sharepoint that it doesn't have to be coming from the store it might be coming from the corporate
catalog or it might be something what where remotely pushing
the science and it's fla ad lighting up functionality and provisioning staff within the within
...itself but it's the loosely coupled model...actual executed outside of
to sharepoint still but it's not really a sharepoint app in the sense that you actually got
a store and download...and it's working in
...frame isolate...way and I want to be really, really clear with folks?
People a lot of times look at our app model they say wow there's, there's all these different options we used to
...now we have to their sharepoint hosted in
...provider hosted I'm going to be very clear with you if you're not
...isv trying to develop and deploy through our store.
You probably shouldn't be looking at sharepoint hosted now there's some instances where it's useful
...enterprise perspective but, you're default thinking should be to the
provider hosted model just because it gives you so much more capability the sand
...sharepoint hosted model does exactly what it was
intended and designed to do which is provide isolation
okay so the data that app rights to is its own little island called and
app web it can't call things outside of its
app domain there's a lot of restrictions we put on there because why because you don't
know that developer who wrote that thing for the store if we let it just inject javascript in your page
and sniff around I mean they could impersonators ceo gosh knows what they could do
...security perspective so sharepoint...really were built with that target in
mind...so trying to jam that into an enterprise scenario I've yet to
see one-b successful...open to okay a lot of people finding compelling because
they don't have to worry about where am I going to host this thing right and that was a lot of
...that-you had for...sharepoint was I just have a sharepoint farm I can
jam my customizations in there I don't have to spin up extra websites I don't have to have this extra infrastructure and that
was very compelling I argue that you probably added more sharepoint
servers to your form a and paid licensing for that then if you to
just stood that custom code up in ios but that's probably a philosophical argument that we could have
...session I just want to be clear the things that you are seeing us
recommend from enterprise side are very much the provider
hosted model okay you won't hear us talking much about sharepoint hosted and there's a reason.
That's a good way of putting that
an one-minute more kind of a slides let's say a final introduction slide
...process line and this is more I a business trip and thinking but this is
...transformation process which will be shared...msdn as well
we've been using in the...we work with our...traces...get a...whenever
...been helping them to translations adapt model and this is a process thinking and I know that the maturity
...audiences developers I'm a developer as well and but we need to also understand the best
...approaching days projects as a want to actually have that slide conquering
...the number one thing to understand is to readiness absolutely
the customer all the people you work with they actually understand what is done-up...does it mean
we have made the decisions about the hosting we know where is going to host that is going to be a
provide a hosted hopefully yes and...going to be now show...kind of been on premises
...service that's number one thing that everybody's leveled up on that one...we do an assessment
...want to really understand what to customize having rightnow within their function within their...the
...solution implementation and that's why we don't actually necessarily even concentrate
...and we've done quite a few of the assessments...responded by looking into
...just go down from solution code but then we realized that actually that doesn't explain how
the inches using the functionality it's much more beneficial to schedule
beatings and demos within the business owners are actually showing this is how we use that...
part we don't actually use so we are able to...those a requirements away how do we do the
translation and then we do planning which is essentially the high-level thinking of
...solution transformation so we know exactly what are the main topics...kind of provide
...applications we need to...asher is a web job is a storage
...whatever we need to...and after that comes the actual implementation this is
...the big base which has been dependent on the previous steps and in our way
of working at quite often actually after that first...stamps that's when we do
estimates...then we...we actually know how...because we know where
heading and with the with the dedicated customers we did actually fixedtimeframe to
one two-step...to entry and after that's then it's the variable because the implementation is
always and debatable...the for what they're doing and then the final state this obviously
the actual deployment of the solution and one of the
...key points here the remember that it's not just getting the absolution
...functionality lined up ...the...for the customer but it also think
about the transformation so how do we actually tackled existing content if we need to
...how do we transform the existing site collections to use...model way of
...way of offering the functionality...able to...solution away from the
fun if needed but there's a lot of thinking that's a lot of an additional ip coming up on this
one in msdn pretty soon and new templates and powerpoint and all of
...which will be...I think that is actually an interesting thing to talk about here visit
and crew have really done a really good job being open...even not just the code
so if you if you hear about office developer patterns and practices you go check out our data repo or you go to
the about office dot com and you and you start reading about that it's not just the code...also sharing
our points and all kinds artifacts that they're using in these engagements and,
that stuff shows up in our get hub repo first and then later
...content publishing folks come through and they they've been publishing it into msdn
and helping us, you know,
massage are wording because we're technical and we don't really care about those things so-if you want-to
see latest and greatest ...get every pose are really the place to go and, then if you want to see
published on msdn so you can point to a customer and say it's official microsoft guidance
then, you know, shortly thereafter...stuff shows up on...
pooch let's move on the demo section so let's forget about one for the above
...let's not forget about the previous...and let's actually move on them all technical and development
oriented...but...wanted to do a demos...actually show you a slightly more and slightly
advance and arias with app model which are not actually showing you the typical story within
apart...lighting up a custom action...kind of an alternative ways of approaching
ad need at scenarios one of the really typical pattern is...javascript and pet
...pattern and to be honest and now we're getting
...recorded us well it was first called javascript injection pattern but then somebody said that
well the injection doesn't sound good to...changed the name to be javascript
embed pattern which is absolutely find it is actually embedding...javascript
into pipeline of the...rendering at which is much more better way of actually explaining that but,
I'm going to explain...slide...going to do a
...on this one so what we're going to do is that as part of the...provisioning...as part of the
...provisioning or as part of the installation of a provide...application,
for example, to app...we actually and reference and,...sites
...using a whipped up custom action collection and what we do
is that we...reference to an external javascript file we don't actually
...and app as such but when we do this reference and,
that the adding the use a custom action to the science are javascript
...then debates rendering and html creation when
we render that paged for the intuition and what it means is that
our javascript and actually taken ownership of the elements on functionality is
what we are showing within the must debate is all within the...and we're able to then bring additional
functionalities what's on available for the...in this particular case we're actually going to show you
how to do a top-level navigation for example, across site collection navigation which is
pretty typical scenario...at the requirement of having a custom must
debate which is one of the decayed practices of thinking in the
windows sharepoint development so-if you-can to add try to have want
to overwrite out-of-the-box must debates and there's this multiple reasons for that we're not going to go to detail
...one we actually have eight hours of virtual academy training out of microsoft virtual
academy if you'd like to go into the weeds with those recommendations so...go too much into that
with this I'm going to cut over to my machine here?
I think.
Wrong button...on.
All right so again if you saw on the slide we have a link in the dec you can get
it later it's out on get hub every one of these demos...on get hub you can pull them down you can
...five them I'm going to show you just a real high-level how that
works so just assume all I've done is I've pulled down this code sample from our get of repo
which is great and it's got a few solutions here couple solutions here it's got my actual
apps app project here my
at manifest that's the part that actually...sharepoint and then it's got a provider hosted
...web project here really all I had to do a...pulled down from get
...is all I had to do was coming here and give it my site url for where my
developer site collection is that was it I pasted the
...developer site collection in my office we sixty-five tenet and now I'm going to come back over here and I'm going to
hit a five so,
I'll show you what it does first and then we'll jump in and we'll actually look at how it's doing it so,
this is a really simple example these types of things are
typically done as part of a site provisioning process you'll hear...talk about things
like remote provisioning that's definitely a pattern that you should get familiar with and,
we can show you a little bit more in subsequent demos?
Input in my password.
Typically...these the first-time you'll get a dialogue that asks if you trust it things inside
...my demo earlier I think I've already trusted but boom everyone of these
samples actually gives you a nice little screen here that talks about what the sample does
...and gives you some buttons to actually do it so you can see here that it's really what this is going to do is
add secondary navigation to my...you would have probably taken approach
of customizing master page or something like that this is an alternate way to do it so,
here what I'm going to...is it says I'm...the second-level navigation so I'm just
...button once that gets done it says that...has been applied to the host
lab I can go back to site and you can see it so basically what I've done.
Is underneath the...the...navigation here prophecy sixty-five I now
have a second-level and I can put whatever links I want in there and,
that's all done with javascript like I said?
So,...I close that let's go look at the actual code so,
if you look at the app manifest itself is really nothing interesting there we're going to
start from behind our default spx I am going to.
Over here a little bit and show you guys.
...scroll them.
The page load really just does the chrome control but if you
look here this is where the actual magic is happening so when I click that button.
It is going to a method called ad js
linked so I'm going to go to the definition of that and this is where.
It happens so you can see here that we're
setting up some urls there were set up a link to our...javascript so we
written some javascript called inject navigation dot js which is part of this project.
And, then here you can see...grabbing a collection of the existing actions so,
the user custom actions that are already applied
to the web we're loading them executing the query and,
then from there we're going...scroll down just a little bit more.
And, you can see from there were actually going through and were checking to see
if are inject navigation is already there if it is we want to delete it and,
then we want to go ahead and riyadh it so that way
...run this thing and updated as many times as I like but,
that really is that's it I'm just setting a user custom action I'm
...some javascript and I'm assigning into the web that's pretty much the media
magic now if you go look at the actual javascript itself
which is under here so we've got inject navigation it's really not
that complex so we've got some you can see here that
were actually using local storage highly
recommend so anybody who's done any really complex navigation queries
and side of sharepoint with full trust code knows those who get quite expensive on
the server so you probably took some support sort of server-side
caching approaches so that your users wouldn't have to suffer through that pain every time
...servers wouldn't come problems there needs you still need to cash you still need to think about cashing but the
...you're probably going to use is most likely on the client-side so think about
these new modern browsers and all the great wonderful things you can do with local
storage or some of the old tried-and-true methods of cookie's those are all still valid but, you know,
perf is still problem even when you're in our cloud and,
you want to make sure that you're doingsome of those types of things so here
we're really just checking to see if something's in the cache locally if it's not?
Here's where we're actually coming in and we're actually injecting a bunch of html.
Into the page pretty option looking staff by pretty ugly
looking stuff but hey, that's actually easy-to-read and camel anybody else's.
But, essentially what we're doing here is that we are transforming the web control way the service
...way of implementing controls user controls composite controls or
whatever left navigation top navigation to be a client-side implementation and where building that
...this javascript and this is just a pretty
...and from a code perspective but it's enabling
...showing the pattern how you can still and bring individual functionality is within the
patrons...think of it this is exactly the same model where how do you embed, for example,
the amr discussion to your sharepointhow do you
embed google maps of being maps to our website you essentially by had achieved
there you have a pointer to the javascript...you reference an external javascript
...essentially test-taking advantage
...thinking it's not an app but we're just adding that's reference that exchange
...which is can then light upstart functionality...can be as complex as possible
or ask simple as possible so it's an alternative way of approaching the whole sharepoint
...transformation or sharepoint that is...by not being forced to
then do an app as such so it's taking advantage of that remote provisioning
thing all of the demos we have a link to our office traces twib develop about
...practices location...where you can actually pinpoint for example,
for that particular example is quite a few examples of what we have already there which
...laney hundred, hundred one...forty or something...a hundred
...individual examples so, one of the things...also wanted to kind of a cover today
it so we didn't want to again we didn't want to go the basic and show you that you can do x and once they wanted
to go slightly more at runs at like steve said earlier the programme has...application is a
...hosted app model is extremely powerful and one of the really powerful
ways of approaching the...app model is taking advantage soft of the services want
...microsoft usher is actually providing...one of the patterns
...being used in which many of our customers is actually taking advantage of access storage
...jobs pretty new technology you might be...of that or...I'm going to
...cruncherfew demos based on the similar thinking but what it actually gives
us is a really needs...process where
...that arrow completely messed up anyway so,
where we where we...again go to provide
...application and ain't...a can start a process the process
itself is actually adding and message the storage q which is essentially you might be
...old-school develop rights message q...msm q at in the on
premises what then will happen is that storage q message will in multiple
...your web chop which are running into microsoft...so at this point benches
has already free to...a...to long-running operation you really don't want to show the key
funny may shun for benches...with take-over...of process, for example,
for provisioning some something on doing long-lasting operation
and at this point whenever the message has been at the storage...freed up so...
I can continue doing something but our task is still ongoing on the background and then the web
chavis actually...it's execute by the stories go any gets that message from the
story scare and then that can actually use the app
...token at to access to sharepoint and...operations against office
...defined...whatever possible means and as an example we're going to do
a slightly more complex demo after this one...for the...provisioning...quick
...on explaining what does this actually mean into practice what do I need to know due to
take advantage of this a synchronous process and how...actually relate from a inches
...experience perspective so if you switch me on the on the screen?
And, that's not me that somebody else.
Navigate that's...again so this is...core dot q web
...use its example really simple example this is not flashes stuff because we're from engineering for
from not from marketing that's the thing and what we're trying to show you different approaches and,
what this one is...that well it has for obviously the typical documentation...do for the
...some practices stuff it has to sharepoint provide a
...that app introduction project and there's...provide...this would be actually running
than within the microsoft...or within the on premises then we have this
joke fellow here which is actually the web...that's the one which will automatically
...a synchronous way start in the cloud and that will then connect...office
traces defined based on the request what the ys actually queuing and then we have a
plaque proper way of implementing any dot net code we have a common business logic component which we
can thenobsessed on-call from any locations so I'm going to do and
I find for this one it's doesn't take long it's going to spin up my process and I will be
then running the dep sample from my local is express?
Do I do want while he's spending that up you know,
better touched on it before but we're showing things in as are obviously you could do these things on
cram but, you wouldn't be able to use asher so you could have
...is website you could look at things like msm q you could you can
stitched together these same types of solutions in your own prime environment but,
it is super awesome the as...team is innovating that fast these services that he's
actually showing you didn't even exist when we started down this journey with our customers...
it was very actually very timely that we were able to get
these services boo started to find out that...know synchronous patterns
against this cloud when you're doing things like site provisioning that takes a while and it's not a great
user experience so with that I think it's very interesting to look at how both
you can utilize the capabilities of badger as they come out with them without
...team sorry having to actually do any investment
in our products to make them available to turn and
...like mention this is rather simple example we're going to do a slightly more complex example as
...final them off the session but this is more about showing you the difference so we do
have to different patterns we have the synchronous operation and
...synchronous operation if you think about the typical synchronous operation it's might take
awhile for benches...checking dangers a process and essential showing some nice
...automation and it's working as...can to do some operation against the sharepoint
sign...essentially are freeing up...and this is not really accurate and years
experience even though natively even office phrases to five actually...that
quite often and what happens in this particular demo this is relatively simple demo
and it's essentially now executed asynchronous operation and a document library create
...operation so it actually created
at one document library addedthe website host web using
...as synchronous approach so I do now have an
one additional document library in my site contents so...going to show you that it actually did
Which is a create using a take number I said but this is not a marketing
demos so this is an engineering...and its to at creating a document library using
...some relatively simple stuff but now the difference on the on the thinking is that the
...approach is actually spinning...and this a synchronous
...so from angels a perspective the operation is extremely fast
...what hanover happened was that the operation was actually added in the storage
...and at the same time would that have been my...stories with job was actually
speedup and that's now actually ongoing and running and within my asher so I'm going to quickly
jump on the microsoft the...so you this one in practice?
Because we should be able to
sell still see and that executions still ongoing so what I have...the microsoft the
...is that I've...which is continuously running...and what that happens this so it's
actually in stop status for some reason...and running status okay what
did an update that what that happens is that whenever I'm adding a new item in the
stories q I have a hooked up with two lines of code
...the web...so it will be executed automatically find a
web of by usher whenever...on the story...so now this web chavis
then taking advantage of the app only token and what it means is that in my
quantify in my app conflict we have...
...we have our configuration...so we have the need at client id and
...client secret actually managed within a...the show...so
...using essentially that client...and client secret now to connect on of
...defined and then we do the modification in a synchronous
way...so then I could have the same code the same project deployed...pointed different
the sites with different you can do whatever you want absolutely because now this the act
...and...has quite a lot of different commissions and it can do much more than
...to create a document library it could start creating a site collections that...creating
...are creating...case of science or collect information within
...and...in this particular case we can actually see also from the microsoft the share
...which is really called the locking system is really awesome so we're able to
axle a-c and the latest implantation and latest executions of the
...and in this case we're able to,
for example, see that the process process...message has been executed and it will success
a one-minute ago so we're able to actually see what's happening within the...
it was able to connect back on the on the sharepoint and most likely in the best possible
wayne if you go back on the that sharepoint science?
Have a look on the host...we actually now have a new document library
...assigned not a suppress exit demo I know but from a thinking perspective and
a synchronous processing perspective it's a huge opportunity
...start running alternative
...alternative processes using the similar way of implementation?
And, quickly looking and the...so, we don't actually need to have...on that one
...during the more complex demos some can access of break point here and I'm going to
click one more time...synchronous operation and this
...for seriously six lines of code...orwell...depending on how many
lines to...a single-line and but this is essentially the operation and
method what we're calling within the are provide a host
of application and we have already created a syria object which is actually
having a url and my request a name and what we're doing is that we are adding and item to the
...within the microsoft to share with taking advantage of the stories
...sdk and we're adding that methods and we are realizing that...storage
...and that's pretty much that's like six lines of code but the map what
...the magic is actually is on the web job
as side itself so in the web chops which has been already deployed on the microsoft
...the only thing what I need to do is make sure that
mike asher connectivity and the...webster's
...storage is point into the same storage asked the...the item which
has adding does items to the q and then actually
test decorate appropriately aone function call
which will then help on me and essentially this will
...whole decoration in here will make sure that whenever there's an item...on the stories
q my web chavis...and then I can actually do whatever the business logic is that
...I need to do so in this particular case as an example...taking advantage of the
app only access token which we need to because we don't have a user
...essentially elevating...this up only access token and then
where accessing the science using that token and modifying the sites as needed?
Relatively simple thing but,
let's actually built on that thinking so let's take that thinking in a slightly
at new level can switch back on the slide.
So, on that same thinking let's take this slightly more on a slightly different
levels so we think about sharepoint...on this all about sites
...provisioning it's all of...typically start from the fact that as an as a
...solution developer used to create side definitions...used to create web templates as an on a xml
...feature frameworks...doing modules now when we are enough
racist define we really want to move away from the feature framework implementation what we want
to do is take advantage of so-called sharepoint remote provisioning what it means is that from a
...perspective we actually create the sites
...collections using see some and we seriously
used to client-side object model to even create the site columns and content...to the
...collections which we create as part of the provisioning and,
on that thinking so essentially from
...a perspective end-user goes to...selects a template...actually...that application
...running on premises...and based on a template...a new science
...on the sharepoint based on the template configuration now as part of hysteresis
divide...by...practices we've been running that program for quite a long-time and...a lot of customers who want
to actually do remote provisioning they want to take advantage of this thinking that we're able to
overrides the whole on at xml and feature framework
...of doing...so...that okay how do identifying what is my template
well you could always create...xml which has than average and transform to be
...see some but then it's still...xml so that's part of the...
bothersome practices guide and we started thinking this engine which is still supporting the xml
approach as well but we can do something really cool so what we can do it is,
for example, the following business scenario the business users...be a
...persons of...a business editors content...which will
...using a process so they will have a dedicated science
...template sites where they will code and create document libraries...
needn't using their process and whenever...a goes to a new and request...a
...collection what are engine will do it on fly which is
open-source available as part of the patterns and practices guidance it actually extracts
the chains is from those live...and provisions new science-based on
...template so this way you don't actually need to
create don't xml you don't have to create feature framework you don't have to create xml
...you don't want to actually create templates within the sharepoint and we can actually bring this to
...that's if a
person we might have multiple different templates we might have individual
templates for hr organization for services organizations for whatever the
organizations within your company and the engine itself is as I
mentioned it's open-source it's available...looking into contribution from the community and
...but it's already in a relatively could...so, what we have is
essentially an engine and I'm showing the key pieces of code because this is extremely
cool stuff we have whenever you add and reference to the...pick core component
...will give you extension methods as long as have a reference that...component you will,
for example,...a method called get provisioning
...probation template and what we can do with that one is extracts and
...that...from any science compared out-of-the-box dame sign or out-of-the-box
publishing site innovator and what we can do with that template
is a domain object it's not an xml at this point
...we can do...is that we're able to serialized...and save that doesn't xml,
for example, the...store or sharepoint list or a plus system if we want to
...but the most magical thing at least from my perspective I'm an old-school on
...developer and is that I can actually use that
template on fly with some extracting that site a and actually apply that to
talk assigned and what will happen is that all the chains is what the ui
what we've done using a process will be applied to...and
it's seriously six lines of code right now if you take advantage of the...and practices
call component which is a community turban program as well so let's actually have a look on this one we do
have four nights at ten minutes time to actually run...the demo...
So, let's stop to previous demo and let's move that this following demo so this
one is provisioning and there's a lot...at this actually video recording which we already released
and channel nine which showing some of this stuff as well.
As is a provisioning framework a
...so it's actually you can find this underneath...solution and...
some practicesguidance but I'm going to do is I'm going to nf five...to show the basic
ui what this solution is doing truy itself is actually not interesting this
...the provide...that application which is showing self-service site collection creation
new and it's after you an...business case what kind of you are you actually want to provide
...into says benton itself is can be used using...shell it can be used using
a consul application and whatever service code within the microsoft...
So, there's our ui this could be at typical self-service high collection creation feeling and,
...a project manager comes...a name like...twenty fifteen
let's give it a url builds twenty fifteen and then
...that can actually select what kind of a template we want to
use the templates themself are actually xml serialized xml of the template
information but I can do is that I can also use and existing site as my
template and that's taking advantage soft the and decor component using
the see some and restful api operating and extracting the information from that live
...that to the target side so this is now my template
...this is my imaginary template time just to make sure that I'm not actually fooling let's do
some small changes on the template time so give me a document library name.
...fool for is not good well we might have been
...somebody else from the audience.
Important documents exxon so let's add a new
...library name.
And, let's create that's and...that important documents.
And, create the document library on that live template sign.
And, now the templates at that new document libraries on...so we know that whenever we
apply the templates we absolutely know that if it's working and that pro
asks a important documents...going to be there the programme has
the application dui science essentially trust what it's doing is that
it's actually taking all the collecting the information within the form...
deciding that's a request and...realizing...can actually show you the object in here.
There we go
...this actually collecting all the url request and timezone request and all of that
...then it's...that to the stories...in the same way...within the previous demos I'm not going to actually work
...on that one now...in a synchronous process so,
right now it's going to tell me your request has been real record it and we'll
pay process tune and that process is now ongoing already in...microsoft
...but technically...defy we don't know-how long it's going to take
...to create a new site collection so what I've done is that within the example us well...
can actually bypass this with a clean...so let me show you
this one this my template...which is that the one where we added that
important documents...going to refresh so making sure that on the left side
in the recent section we have the important document this minus
site so this is essentially we always start by creating a new site using out-of-the-box sites
and template or out-of-the-box...definitions to be precise from a
...so what will happen for that ...twenty...create a site collection using
...sign and then it will apply...modifications on top of it so let's do this manuallywithin the
project we have a bypass so-called...project so
which is called a helper apply custom template what that this is
the consul application which is using essentially ...token
it's asking what is my template site which is extracting and what is my talk at site
...applying and then we're able to have a look on the code as well so I'm going to just go here
it's asking my template site...copy...template site url?
Udp where's my consul application...that...
And, this my target...url.
On-base things about...as well and what's going to now happen is
that the engine itself it's can actually do...point pretty
soon on the meaningful topic and meaningful url so we have that
skate provisioning template extension method in a web object and what I can do with
that one is that I'm calling...and it's going to extract me a domain object which will be
act essentially containing all the modifications what has been
applied to that sites that template signed on top of out-of-the-box team
and team sign so it's doing a delta compilation and it's giving me all of those change
...which...been applied to that sign and after a few seconds
...depending...timing is dependent on how many customizations
...we have that template object now exists and I can actually do something like?
Come on, immediate window how do I
clear immediate window not a clear hundred lsm...sorry.
I can that let's read this one so I'm going to zoom in san ovaries and templates
I can do lists and, I can do...can...zooming
in a second so...showing me how many list of actually have on that site
...able to say that as a one list we're able to do
the list so it's a template object which I can modifying also on
...in the memory so I can build on top of that extractor template if
...this my important documents which is which was extract from the
...and now what we're doing in the following step is then we are applying
dot to the target sign so essentially this my apply probation a template thats when
that's my data object or the domain object and again where using then the see some
...the restful api to remote operations to now modified to target
...based on our configuration and like mention...the start and...as
and xml configuration as a template if needed if you want to have a selection of individual templates
and options its again...to you on a business case danger itself is highly flexible
...from that perspective?
Well, he's weight on to apply allows you might be saying well you just showed
we save side is template with a whole bunch of code.
No,
we didn't has anyone here use save side is a template in...sixty-five
...with...lovett are at so there's a lot of real challenges with
save side is a template not the least of which it doesn't work against publishing sites if there's been an app
activated on this site you can't save side as a template there's a huge number of restrictions there
also it generates a definition for that site and then publishes
you when you're creating site subsequently off of that template uses that definition if we add new features and
...sixty-five or we do things you have to go recreate those templates
...you may or may not want to get
on that train I'm thinking not typically you want to own the
site provisioning process and have a little bit more granular control over it and,
this is really what drove us to build this and patterns?
And, now if we if you are watching
...ios refreshing dui it was actually krajina applying does change says we've got
to important documents we got the branding we got the logos and all of the settings
...to the level of site collections as
...as site columns content pipes and all of that views and all of those settings
...able to see that essential and the target science my template...the at
it has been applied the template on flying extracted on flying from the landslide and applied
...life on a five site without any need of creating but templates are on...to framework
...super cool stuff at least from my perspective we.
Yeah, switching back...where slightly running out of time well, not that much we do have fifty seconds and
...but anyway I think the key point of the thing is that
...see some as the feature the app model is definitely the
...what-you want-to do as a developer you really want to take advantage so far
at developer program and you want to go to the deft office a calms last
...program and this email letters newsletters free...dictionary
developer subscription so I if you don't already have one of those is a great way to develop
prophecy sixty-five without have to pay ninety nine bucks if we got questions can come to the mike?
Well, for the recording so guide registering and sending us to
...for pagenow and, there's an office phrases
...the in the second...floor that would be the way to go.
Good I think that's all we're going to actually todayso,
please take advantage of that that's offering
and hopefully demo us cool from a template thinking perspective take advantage of
...practices guidance as well and give us feedback that's the
most important thing thank you thank you.